Guide to the Oscar Serlin Collection of George Bernard Shaw Materials, 1920-2006 (bulk 1920-1951)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Oscar Serlin Collection of George Bernard Shaw Materials
1920-2006
1920-1951
Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Serlin, Oscar, 1901-1971, collector.
2 cubic feet (4 boxes, 4 map folders, 2 framed items, 1 sculpture)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Portraits of George Bernard Shaw, as well as photographs, framed materials, notes, and memorabilia relating to Shaw.
Biographical Note
George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950) was one of the most important English-language writers to emerge during the second half of the nineteenth century. Born in Dublin, Ireland, Shaw moved to London in 1876, where he rose to fame as a playwright, journalist, arts critic, political essayist, and polemical speaker. Best known now as a dramatist, Shaw wrote plays that addressed most of the important philosophical, religious, social, economic, and political issues of his time. The influence of his dramas was immense and, as the portraits in this collection suggest, that influence extended beyond the literary and into the visual arts.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains portraits of George Bernard Shaw, as well as photographs, framed materials, a sculpture, notes for Shaw's play The Shewing Up of Blanco Postnet, and memorabilia relating to Shaw.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the
Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Martin-Harvey, John, Sir, 1863-1944; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950
Subjects:
Authors, Irish; Portraits, American; Portraits, European
Document Types:
Drawings (visual works); Photographs; Portraits; Sculpture (visual works); Woodcuts (prints)
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, January 2012. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, May 2023.
Custodial History
These materials were collected by film and theater producer Oscar Serlin over the course of his career.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Oscar Serlin, August 1977.
Series List
- Series I. Portraits, 1935-2006, undated
  This series consists of portraits of George Bernard Shaw by various American, British, and European artists. Although most of the portraits are undated, they were all most likely created between 1930 and 1951.
  Arranged alphabetically by artist name.
- Series II. Miscellaneous Materials, 1920 - circa 1938
  This series consists of a variety of items by or related to Shaw, including memorabilia such as a portrait medallion and 5 postcards printed with pre-written messages declining various requests; photographs, mainly of actor Sir John Martin-Harvey costumed for or performing in a 1926 production of Shaw's play The Shewing Up of Blanco Posnet; Shaw's notes and sketches for The Shewing Up of Blanco Posnet; a scrapbook of photographs and clippings gifted to Shaw by William Randolph Hearst; and a bronze statue of Shaw by sculptor Ralph C. Scott.
  Arranged alphabetically.
Container List
- Series I. Portraits, 1935-2006, undated
  - Berger, Oscar, undated; [black crayon drawing on paper] (Folder 2.1)
  - Cotton, William D., "Saint George,", undated; [pastel painting on paper] (Folder 2.13)
  - Garfield, Frances O'Brien, undated; [green and black woodcut on paper] (Folder 2.2)
  - Havens, James D., "Pshaw,", 1935; [colored woodcut on paper] (Folder 2.3)
  - Hirschfeld, Albert, undated; [Black ink drawing on paper] (Folder 2.4)
  - Hoffman, Irving, undated; [brush and ink drawing on paper] (Folder 2.5)
  - Leaver, Noel Harry, [1951?]; [black India ink wash drawing on paper] (Map Case Folder 30.1)
  - Marcus, Seymour, undated (Folder 2.6)
  - Mrowzewski, Stefen, circa 1935; [sepia wood engraving on paper] (Folder 1.1)
  - Mrowzewski, Stefen, circa 1935; [sepia wood engraving on paper] (Folder 1.2)
  - Mrowzewski, Stefen, circa 1935; [sepia wood engraving on paper] (Folder 2.7)
  - Norkin, undated; [pen and brush India ink drawing on paper] (Folder 2.8)
  - Roos, Birger, undated; [pen and ink drawing on tracing paper] (Folder 1.3)
  - Roos, Birger, undated; [pen and ink drawing on tracing paper] (Folder 2.9)
  - Roos, Birger, undated; [6 India ink drawings on paper] (Map Case Folder 30.2)
  - Rovson, John, undated; [brush and ink drawing paper] (Folder 2.10)
  - Sandar, Barry, 1949; [ink drawing on paper] (Folder 1.4)
  - Sappol, undated; [black brush and ink drawing on paper] (Folder 2.11)
  - Stone, Walter King, undated; [ink drawing on paper] (Folder 1.5)
  - Tittle, Walter Ernest, undated; [black and white etching on paper] (Folder 3.1)
  - Tittle, Walter Ernest, undated; [black and white etching on paper] (Folder 3.2)
  - Tittle, Walter Ernest, "After my own portrait painted from life - Walter Tittle,", undated; [black and white etching on paper] (Folder 3.3)
  - Topolski, Feliks, [1943?]; [black crayon drawing on beige paper] (Folder 3.6)
  - Topolski, Feliks, undated; [pen and ink drawing on paper] (Folder 3.4)
  - Topolski, Feliks, "90th Birthday,", 1946 July 26; [gouache painting on gray paper] (Map Case Folder 30.3)
  - Topolski, Feliks, "90th Birthday,", 2006; [reproduction on foamboard] (Folder 3.5)
  - Tukob, M., 1943; [black and white woodcut on paper] (Folder 3.7)
- Series II. Miscellaneous Materials, 1920 - circa 1938
  - Drawings - Farleigh, John, "Tell Her to Go to the Devil," sketch of a scene from Back to Methuselah with notes by George Bernard Shaw, circa 1938; [pencil on paper, framed] (Framed Storage 2.5)
  - Drawings - Unidentified artist, drafts of a broadside advertising "Martin-Harvey in The Devil's Disciple,", undated; [charcoal and colored chalk on paper. 2 black-and-white, 1 color] (Map Case Folder 30.4)
  - Drawings - Unidentified artist, silhouettes of figures in theatrical costume, undated; [black ink on paper] (Folder 1.9)
  - Notes and sketches by Shaw on The Shewing Up of Blanco Posnet, undated (Folder 1.7)
  - Photograph - Portrait of George Bernard Shaw, undated (Folder 1.8)
  - Photograph - Portrait of George Bernard Shaw, taken by himself circa 1906 and printed by F. H. Evans, with note and signature by Shaw, 1930 Jan 12; [reproduction] (Folder 2.12)
  - Photograph - Sir John Martin-Harvey in costume as Blanco Postnet, circa 1920 (Folder 1.7)
  - Photographs - Sir John Martin-Harvey in costume as Blanco Posnet, circa 1920; [2 photographs] (Folder 1.8)
  - Photographs - Sir John Martin-Harvey in a performance of The Shewing Up of Blanco Posnet at the London Coliseum, 1920 Oct 26; [4 photographs] (Folder 1.8)
  - Portrait medallion of Shaw by an unidentified artist, undated (Folder 1.6)
  - Postcards - Pre-written response messages declining a variety of requests, undated; [5 postcards] (Folder 1.11)
  - Poster - Pan American World Airways, "Ireland by Clipper," featuring a quotation from George Bernard Shaw, undated; [color lithograph, framed, 39.5 x 26.5 inches] (Framed Storage 2.8)
  - Proofs of Shaw's Preface to Great Expectations by Charles Dickens, 1936 Dec (Folder 1.10)
  - Scrapbook presented to Shaw by William Randolph Hearst, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Sculpture - Scott, Ralph C., bronze statue of Shaw, undated; [21 inches] (Reading Room)